(
"ai_sub_version": "3.5.2",
"generated_at": "2026-08-27T01:03:24.192386",
"lyrics_prompt_version": 9,
"subtitles_prompt_version": 18,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"any_pending": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": null,
"model_subtitles": "google-gla:gemini-3.6-flash",
"model_lyrics": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true,
"max_storage_gb": 18.0
),
"search": (
"qps": 0.3,
"max_length": 4096,
"web_search_tool": "langsearch",
"timeout": 60.0,
"retries": 3,
"min_wait_seconds": 1.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 10.0,
"multiplier": 2.0
),
"validation_buffer_ms": 2000,
"verification_gap_seconds": 60,
"gap_verification_retries": 1,
"gap_verification_ignore_start": true,
"gap_verification_ignore_end": true
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": false,
"fps": 1.0,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"threshold_mb": 20,
"duration_tolerance_ms": 100,
"encoder": null
),
"start_offset_min": 0
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"lyrics": 4,
"subtitles": 4
),
"retry": (
"per_run": 5,
"max_runs": 3,
"multiplier": 2.0,
"min_wait_seconds": 30.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 300
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": true,
"scrub": false,
"progress_bars": true,
"progress_bar_width": 80,
"progress_bar_refresh_seconds": 1.0
)
ちわーす！ホロライブ2期生、大空スバル！
Hello there! Hololive 2nd Gen, Oozora Subaru!
1級船舶免許を取ってからなんと1年が経ちました！大空スバルです！
It's already been a year since I got my Class 1 boat license! I'm Oozora Subaru!
今回はロケに来ております！
We are shooting on location today!
ゲストはミオしゃ〜！
Our guest is Mio-sha~!
はーい！うち、うち、うちだよ！大神ミオだよ！ホロライブゲーマーズの大神ミオです！
Hi! It's me, me, me! Ookami Mio! Hololive Gamers' Ookami Mio!
今日は来てくれてありがとう！
Thanks for coming today!
呼ばれたには呼ばれたけど…今日何をするんでしょうか？
I came because you invited me... but what are we doing today?
今日の企画言っちゃっていいわけ？
Can I reveal today's plan?
あー、じゃあ言っちゃってもらって…
Ah, sure, go ahead...
大空スバル、いざ大海原へ！ミオしゃを海のドライブに連れて行く！
Oozora Subaru, off to the open sea! Taking Mio-sha on an ocean drive!
大空クルーズ第1号のお客様がミオしゃに決定しましたー！
Mio-sha has been chosen as Passenger No. 1 for Oozora Cruise!
いやいやいや…ガチで怖いから…ガチで…
No no no... That's seriously scary... Seriously...
大丈夫、大丈夫！ガチ免許あるから！免許！
It's fine, it's fine! I have a real license! A real one!
シオンと取った免許あるから大丈夫…
I got my license with Shion, so it's fine...
免許取りたての運転ほど怖い事ねぇじゃん！
Nothing's scarier than driving with a fresh license!
しかも一回スバル、個人的にちゃんと運転しに行ってるから！
Plus, I actually went boat driving on my own once!
あ、練習済みってこと？
Oh, so you've practiced?
そう、練習もしてきたから！任せてよ！学科の成績良かったから！
Yeah, I practiced! Leave it to me! My written exam scores were great!
しかもミオしゃと言えば釣りでしょ？
Besides, when you think of Mio-sha, you think of fishing, right?
そんな事ないからね！
Hey, that's not true!
ミオしゃと言えば釣りだから！釣りして美味い魚食おうよ！
Mio-sha means fishing! Let's go fishing and eat tasty fish!
今日は船釣りするって事？
So we're going boat fishing today?
そう！船釣りをします！スバル免許取ったんですけど、船の運転は本当に危なくて…
Yep! We're boat fishing! I got my license, but operating a boat is really dangerous...
やめてよ！不安になるような事言うの…
Stop that! Don't say things that make me anxious...
死にたくなかったら見張り手伝って欲しい、ほんとに！
If you don't want to die, help keep watch today, for real!
怖いよ〜！！
That's scary~!!
船の事故って結構多いんだって！
Apparently, boat accidents happen pretty often!
そうなんだ〜！
Is that so~!
だから海に入る以上！安全についてもしっかり学ばないといけない！
So since we're going out to sea, we must properly learn about safety!
今回はなんと！海上保安庁さんのご協力いただいております！
This time, we have the cooperation of the Japan Coast Guard!
えぇ！？海上保安庁！？
Eh!? The Coast Guard!?
海の安全について色々教えてくれるみたいなので早速行ってみよう！
They'll teach us all about sea safety, so let's check it out!
という事で！今回ご協力いただく秋山さんです！よろしくお願いします！
So! Joining us today is Akiyama-san! Please go ahead!
よろしくお願いします。千葉海上保安部の秋山です。今日は一緒に勉強していきましょう！
Nice to meet you. I'm Akiyama from Chiba Coast Guard. Let's study together today!
よろしくお願いします！
Nice to meet you!
今日はなんと！船の運転にあたって色々教えていただけると聞いたんですけれど、よろしくお願いします！
I heard you'll be teaching us about boat operation today. We're in your hands!
海を安全に楽しむためのポイントをクイズを交えてご紹介させていただきたい
I'd like to share key points for safely enjoying the sea through a quiz.
ミオしゃ聞いた？クイズだって…！
Mio-sha, did you hear that? A quiz...!
ウチは何も知らないよ？スバルだけが答えるってコト？
I don't know anything, you know? Does that mean only Subaru answers?
協力しようって気は無いの？お前！
Don't you have any desire to help out, you?!
当事者意識！当事者意識！
Sense of ownership! Take some ownership!
低めかもしれない…
Mine might be a bit low...
ミスれねぇんだこれ…
I can't mess this up...
え、ミスれないの？
Wait, you can't fail?
スバルがちゃんと答えてみなさんに伝えるって事ですよね？
Because Subaru answering correctly and teaching everyone is the whole point, right?
はい、そうです！
Yes, exactly!
それじゃあ秋山さん！よろしくお願いします！
Alright, Akiyama-san, please take it away!
よろしくお願いします。
My pleasure.
日本の領土は約38万km2で世界61位の面積なんですけれども、領土を取り囲む領海・排他的経済水域を含めると、約447万km2で世界でも10位以内の数字となっています。
Japan's land area is ~380,000 km² (61st globally), but including its territorial waters and EEZ, it spans ~4.47 million km², ranking in the top 10 worldwide.
日本って島国じゃん！周りに海がいっぱいあるから！
Japan is an island nation! It's because it's surrounded by so much sea!
海上保安庁はこの広大なエリアを11の管区に分け、約15,000人で24時間365日守り続けている！
The Coast Guard divides this vast area into 11 regions, with ~15,000 officers protecting it 24/7, 365 days a year!
え！凄いよ！15000人だけなんだよ？
Whoa, amazing! There are only 15,000 of them?!
海上保安庁は少ない人数で頑張っているので、スバルさん！良かったら海上保安官になりませんか！
The Coast Guard operates with a small team, so Subaru-san, would you like to become an officer?
入っちゃおうかな！
Maybe I will!
スカウトされてる！YAGOOバイバイ！俺海上保安官になる！
She's getting scouted! Bye-bye, YAGOO! I'm joining the Coast Guard!
大丈夫そうかな？結構ポンコツですよ？
Are you sure? She's pretty clumsy, you know.
忘れ物とか結構スゴい…大丈夫ですかね？
She forgets things all the time... Are you sure about this?
どういう人が適性がある？
What kind of person is suitable?
スバルさんのように真面目な方！
Someone as earnest as Subaru-san!
次は、海でのレジャーが事故にならないように自分の命を救うための3つの基本
Next, here are 3 basic rules to protect your life so sea leisure stays safe and fun.
1. ライフジャケットの常時着用！着用しているだけで助かる確率が4倍に！
1. Wear a life jacket at all times! Wearing one increases survival rates fourfold!
海でマリンレジャーを楽しむ際にはライフジャケットの常時着用をお願いします
When enjoying marine leisure, please wear a life jacket at all times.
ただし正しく着用していなかったり古いと膨らまなかったりするので正しい着用と点検を！
However, if worn incorrectly or old, it may fail to inflate, so ensure proper fit and checks!
はい！分かりました！
Yes! Got it!
2. 携帯電話等の連絡手段の確保！
2. Secure communication means like mobile phones!
海で事故に遭った際いち早く連絡することが重要！スマホは防水ケースに！
It's vital to call for help quickly in an accident! Keep your phone in a waterproof pouch!
おー！なるほどね！
Ooh! I see!
警察には110番
Just as you call 110 for the police
消防には119番といった番号と同様に
and 119 for the fire department,
海上保安庁にも緊急通報用の電話番号があるのですが
the Japan Coast Guard also has an emergency phone number.
皆さんご存じですか？
Does everyone know what it is?
えー知らなかったウチは！
Eh? I had no idea!
スバル知ってるこれ！
Subaru knows this one!
1級小型免許をお持ちのスバルさんなら当然知っていると思います
Since Subaru holds a Class 1 Small Vessel License, I'm sure she knows it.
やば 圧ヤバい！圧ヤバい！
Oh no, the pressure is crazy!
海の事件・事故は118番！
For incidents and accidents at sea, call 118!
すごいレス！正解です！
Awesome! That's correct!
おおー！よかったー！あぶねー！
Ooh! Thank goodness! That was close!
ここからは本格的に何問かクイズを出題していきたいと思います！
From here on, I'd like to ask a few serious quiz questions!
やばい！さっきの序章だったんだって！
Oh no! She says that was just the intro!
え！そうなの！？がっつりクイズかと思ってたら...
Eh! Really!? I thought that was already the main quiz...
これから海に出るスバルさんに海上交通のルールについて質問です！
For Subaru, who is about to head out to sea, here is a question about maritime traffic rules!
こちらにスバルさんが操船している船と 右側にミオさんが乗っている船があります
Here we have the boat Subaru is navigating, and on the right, the boat Mio is on.
このままではぶつかってしまう恐れがあるため スバルさんが取るべき行動は次のうちどれでしょう？
At this rate, there's a risk of collision. Which action should Subaru take?
ミオちゃん分かるわけ？
Mio-chan, do you know?
この距離感だったら急げば行ける！みたいな感じになりそうじゃない？
With this distance, feels like you could make it if you hurry, right?
ふっはー！そんなわけはないのだ！
Fuhaha! There's no way!
これスバルね 船舶免許で勉強したことある！これ知ってる！
Subaru studied this for her boat license! I know this!
これは4番！右に舵を切り 相手を避ける！です！
This is option 4! Turn the helm right to avoid the other vessel!
正解は4番です！
The correct answer is number 4!
おおー！そうなんだ！
Ooh! So that's how it is!
このような状況では海上衝突予防法という法律によって 相手を右側に見る船舶が相手を避ける必要があるんです
In this situation, under the Prevention of Collisions at Sea regulations, the vessel seeing another on its starboard side must yield.
この場合はスバルさんの船が右に舵を切って避けるか 減速または停止してミオさんの船を避けるのが正解になります
So in this case, Subaru's boat turning right to avoid, or slowing down/stopping for Mio's boat, is correct.
スバルこういう時もう怖いから止まっちゃいます 「先に行ってください」って！
Subaru gets scared in these situations, so I just stop and say "Please go ahead!"
あー！でも止まってもいいってことですもんね！
Ah! But that means stopping is also allowed, right?
次の問題！
Next question!
ここに架空の湾 スバル湾があります
Here we have a fictional bay, "Subaru Bay".
船が入港するために スバル航路を通って入港します
To enter port, vessels travel through the Subaru Fairway.
航路のここに設置される航路標識の組み合わせをこの中からお答えください
Please choose the correct combination of fairway marks to be placed here from these options.
船舶免許持ってるので分かります！
I have a boat license, so I know this!
これは右舷標識と左舷標識なので...
These are starboard lateral marks and port lateral marks, so...
赤い三角形の方が右で...
The red triangle one goes on the right...
緑の四角の方が左側に入ります！で 上も同様に入ります！
The green square one goes on the left side! And the top ones are arranged the same way!
へぇー！
Heh~!
スバルさん さすがです！
Impressive as expected, Subaru-san!
あぶねー！ちゃんと分かってた！
Phew, close! You really knew it!
では 次の問題です！
Now, on to the next question!
ここに航路標識を設置して船に対して「標識の西側は安全に走れますよ」ということを示したいのですが...
We want to place a seamark here to indicate to vessels that "the west side of the mark is safe to navigate"...
その場合 この4つのうちどれを設置すればいいと思いますか？
In that case, which of these four marks should be installed?
ヤバイよミオちゃん... これはちょっと難しいよ...
This is bad, Mio-chan... This one is a bit tough...
ウチは全然さっぱり！0%分かりません！
I have zero clue! 0% understanding!
え でも多分一番右のやつだった気がします！
Eh, but I think it's probably the one on the far right!
え その心は？
Eh? What's your reasoning?
その心は... なんか一番右に置いてあるやつが西なんだよ
My reasoning... the one placed on the far right means "West".
で 上上ってなってるやつが...
And the one with two upward cones...
下下下が南で...
The one pointing down-down is "South"...
こう ダイヤのマークになっているやつが東なんじゃないかな...
And the one forming a diamond shape must be "East"...
なるほど！方角を表してるってこと？
I see! You mean they represent compass directions?
スバルさん 正解です！
Subaru-san, that is correct!
危ない 危ない！
That was close, that was close!
もう海上保安庁さんで間違えたら免許剥奪されちゃう！
If I got it wrong in front of the Coast Guard, they'd revoke my license!
この航路標識は方位標識と呼ばれるもので それぞれの標識の東西南北側に安全に走れる場所があることを示しています
These fairway marks are called "Cardinal Marks", indicating that safe navigable water lies to the East, West, North, or South of the mark.
本格的なクイズで海難防止について勉強していきましたが 船の事故についてもご紹介させてください！
We've learned about marine accident prevention through these quizzes, but now let us cover vessel accidents as well!
令和7年に海上保安庁が取り扱った船の事故は1,711隻であり そのうち約半数の833隻がプレジャーボートでの事故となっています
In 2025, the Japan Coast Guard handled 1,711 vessel accidents, about half of which (833 vessels) were pleasure boat accidents.
プレジャーボートって何？
What's a pleasure boat?
なんかスバルの乗れる すごいみんなで遊んだりとかするやつ！
It's the kind Subaru can operate, used for leisure with everyone!
あー 観光用の船みたいな？
Ah, like a boat for sightseeing?
この事故のうち約7割が船の整備不良や見張り不十分といった人為的要因と呼ばれる事故となっているんです
About 70% of these accidents are caused by human error, such as poor vessel maintenance or insufficient lookout.
プレジャーボートを操船する方は出港前点検・適切な見張りの実施を行い 事故を未然に防ぎましょう！
Those operating pleasure boats should perform pre-departure inspections and maintain a proper lookout to prevent accidents!
出港前点検の実施はプレジャーボートの事故ではエンジントラブルが多くを占めているんです
Regarding pre-departure inspections, engine trouble accounts for a large portion of pleasure boat accidents.
船が動かなくなったことによって流されて浅瀬に乗り上げてしまったり 他の船にぶつかって二次災害に繋がることもあることから 出港前点検は必ず実施して船を適切に管理しましょう
If a boat loses power, it can drift onto shallows or collide with other vessels causing secondary disasters, so always conduct pre-departure checks and maintain your vessel properly.
そして見張りの実施が安全運行の基本です
Additionally, maintaining a lookout is fundamental to safe navigation.
海は広く他の船とぶつかってしまう恐れはないと思われがちなのですが 見張り不十分による船同士の衝突は多く発生しているんです
It's often assumed that the sea is wide and collisions are unlikely, but many collisions occur due to inadequate lookouts.
船長だけではなく ミオさんのように船に乗っている人たちにも常に見張りを行って 事故を防いでください
Not just the captain, but passengers like Mio-chan as well, should keep a lookout at all times to prevent accidents.
ウチも見てなきゃいけないってコト？
You mean we have to keep watch too?
当たり前じゃん！
Of course!
○にたくなかったら見張りしてないとさ
If you don't wanna die, you gotta keep watch!
怖ぇ！
Scary!
でも見張りは本当に大事って めちゃめちゃ言われたから！
They repeatedly told us keeping watch is super important!
え、めっちゃ大事ですよね？
Wait, it's super important, right?
はい、とても大切です。見張りの基本は、全方位にあたり、対象物を特定せず、継続的に繰り返して行うことが重要です。
Yes, it is very important. The key to keeping watch is to look in all directions without focusing on a single object, and to do so continuously.
へぇ〜
I see...
じゃあウチも見張り… 頑張ります！
Then I'll do my best... to keep watch too!
頑張ってね
Good luck!
という事で！ 今回ご協力いただいた 海上保安庁の秋山さん！
And so! Akiyama-san from the Coast Guard, who helped us out today!
本当にありがとうございました！
Thank you so much!
ありがとうございました！
Thank you very much!
いっぱい釣れるといいですね！
I hope you catch a lot of fish!
行っていらっしゃい！
Have a safe trip!
行ってきます！
Here we go!
いっぱい釣るぞ！
We're gonna catch a lot!
という事で、乗船しました！
And with that, we've boarded!
これがスバルの船…？
Is this Subaru's boat...?
これがスバルの船らしいです。結構デカくてビビってます！
Apparently this is Subaru's boat. It's pretty big, so I'm scared!
デカくてビビってるって事は これレンタルだよね？多分
If you're scared by how big it is, this must be a rental, right?
そうだよ！これレンタルさせていただきました！
That's right! We were allowed to rent this!
今回はですね、セントラルさんの「東京湾フィッシング」に参加します！
Today, we're joining Central's "Tokyo Bay Fishing"!
わー！
Wow!
木更津沖から気軽に楽しめるフィッシングプランで、なんとね、ベテランスタッフさんのサポートを受けながらボートフィッシングが楽しめるという事で！
It's a fishing plan you can easily enjoy off Kisarazu, and you get to enjoy boat fishing with veteran staff support!
それは安心だね！
That's reassuring!
ところがどっこい！
However!
普段はですね、スタッフさんが操縦するんですけど
Normally, the staff steer the boat, but...
はい
Yes.
今回は許可を頂いたので、スバルが運転します！
Since we got permission today, Subaru will be driving!
えー！
Ehh?!
ええ…それ、でもあの…
Uh... but wait, umm...
釣りをするって事だよね？
We're going fishing, right?
そうだよ、今日は釣りをするよ
Yeah, we're fishing today.
ポイントとか分かってるわけ？
Do you even know the spots?
分かんない！だからね、スタッフさんに教えてもらおうと思います！
Nope! That's why we'll ask the staff to show us!
なるほどね
I see.
ちなみに今回はね、シロギスっていうのを釣るらしい！やったことある？
By the way, today we're going for Japanese whiting! Ever done that?
え、ない！
Eh, no!
入れ食いらしい！
Apparently they're biting like crazy!
入れ食い！？
Biting like crazy?!
信じてるぞ！
I believe in them!
本当かなぁ、それ？
I wonder if that's true...
信じてるぞ、セントラルさん！
I'm trusting you, Central!
まあ行ってみましょうよ！
Well, let's give it a try!
はい
Okay!
という事で！出発準備OK！ミオしゃ準備はいいか？
So then! Ready for departure! Mio-sha, are you ready?
いつでも行くぞ！
Ready whenever you are!
それじゃあ、大空スバル号、出航！
Alright, Oozora Subaru-go, setting sail!
出航！
Setting sail!
行くぞ！
Here we go!
運転できるのか…本当に…
Can she really drive...?
まずゆっくり発進
First, a slow start...
やべえ！軽い！
Oh damn! It's so light!
軽い…？
Light...?
やべ、めっちゃ軽い！ちょっと待って！
Whoa, it's super light! Wait a second!
大丈夫だから！
It's fine!
ああああああ！
AAAAAAAH!
このままだと前方の船に突っ込みそうな感じだけど大丈夫…？
At this rate, it feels like we're gonna crash into that boat ahead, are we okay...?
左から曲がっていきます
I'm turning from the left!
そうですね
Right.
おー
Ooh~
やべ、めっちゃ軽い
Whoa, it's so light!
軽いとなにか問題が？
Is it a problem if it's light?
軽いと、ギュウウウンって加速する！
If it's light, it zooms forward super fast!
あ、なるほどね
Ah, I see!
うわ〜！なにこの揺れ！
Whoa~! What is this shaking?!
すぐ30出るやん！
It easily hits 30!
うわー！すごい！めっちゃ曲がる！
Whoa~! Incredible! It turns so much!
操縦しやすいって事？
Does that mean it's easy to steer?
ちょっと慣れないかも！ちょっと慣れていく
I might not be used to this! I'm slowly getting the hang of it.
ゆれゆれある
It's so bumpy.
やべぇ！ゆっくり
Oh crap! Slow down.
死にたくなかったら見張ってくれ！
If you don't wanna die, keep watch!
頼むぞ！
I'm counting on you!
前方に何かデッカいの浮いてる
There's something huge floating up ahead!
デッカいの浮いてる？
Something huge floating?
なんか浮いてる
Something is floating.
何あれ？
What is that?
前のさ船がいるジャン
There's a boat ahead of us, right?
はい
Yes.
あの船がさ、同じ方向に行こうとしてるんだけどさ
That boat is trying to go in the same direction as us...
確かにね
True.
船の後ろも行っちゃダメだからさ、追い抜いた方がいいんだけど
We shouldn't go right behind it either, so it's better to pass it, but...
スバルにそんな度胸はない
Subaru doesn't have the guts for that!
うわぁ！すっげぇ曲がる！
Whoa! It turns so much!
舵持ってかれてるよ！
The helm is taking control!
海運転ムズい！
Driving on the sea is hard!
持ってかれる？
Is it pulling away?
よく分かんない方に曲がる
It turns in weird directions.
潮の流れとかがあるのかな…？
Maybe it's the ocean current...?
こんなに波立ってるとこでこんなデカいの運転した事ないかも
I've never driven something this big where the waves are this rough!
意外と波は立ってるんですか船長？
Are the waves actually pretty rough, Captain?
体感だいぶ立ってますね
It definitely feels pretty rough!
あ、そうなんだ
Oh, really?
どう、スバル船長の運転は？
How's Captain Subaru's driving?
まだ不安はあるけど…
I'm still a bit anxious, but...
うん
Yeah.
この調子であれば事故りはしなさそう
At this rate, it seems like we won't crash.
スバルビビリだからな！やばくなったらエンジン止めるから
Subaru is a scaredy-cat! If things get bad, I'll stop the engine!
エンジン切っちゃうんだ
You'll just turn off the engine?
避けてくださいのスタンスでいく
I'm sticking with the "Please move out of my way" stance!
なるほどね
I see.
多分スピード出した方が揺れ少ない気がする
I feel like going faster actually makes it less bumpy.
それはそう！
That's true!
それはそうなんだけどさ！あの船を抜かすまでは…何があるか分からん！
That's true, but... until we pass that boat, who knows what'll happen!
ね、あの船ちょっと怖いね
Yeah, that boat is a bit scary.
この間通る系苦手なんだよ、マジで！
I'm really bad at passing between things, seriously!
心理ストレスがやばい！
The mental stress is crazy!
あの船あそこ曲がろうとしている気がする
I feel like that boat is trying to turn over there.
右側にちょっとずつ
Steadily heading to the right...
そうだよね
Right.
どうですか初海ライド？
How's your first time riding on the sea?
怖ぇ！
Scary!
怖い？
Scary?
てか、こんなにいっぱい船がいる所知らない
Honestly, I've never been anywhere with so many boats!
俺今まで…
Up until now, I've...
そうなの？
Really?
家の庭でずっと走ってたんや！
I was just driving around in my back yard!
じゃあ結構緊張感あるね！
Then you must be pretty tense!
緊張感あるよ！
I'm super tense!
ミオしゃん、あれ！
Mio-sha, look at that!
うん
Yeah?
あれさっき習ったやつ！
That's what we just learned about!
あーあれ！ブイブイ！
Ah, that! Buoys, buoys!
あれよ！海上保安庁さんが付けてくれてるやつ！
That's the buoy the Coast Guard set up for us!
ホンマありがとー！
Thanks a lot!
ありがとうございます！
Thank you very much!
うわー海に出るー！
Whoa, we're out on the open sea!
やべぇ、ガチで海じゃん！
Holy crap, it's totally open ocean!
ちょっと待って！やばすぎ！
Wait a minute! This is insane!
海だ〜！
The sea~!
海じゃん！
It's the ocean!
こんだけ広かったら安心感あるんじゃない？
When it's this wide open, doesn't it feel safer?
あるある！
Yeah, totally!
初めてこんなレーダーみたいな見たわ！
First time I've ever seen a radar display like this!
おー！
Ohh~!
あの辺じゃね？
Isn't it around there?
この辺だ！
It's around here!
もういいのかな？始めて
Can we start now?
始めちゃう？行くぞ！
Shall we begin? Here goes!
フィッショ！
Fish on!
それで底に着くのを待つ
And then we wait for it to reach the bottom.
着いたかも！
It might have hit the bottom!
着いたかな？
Did it reach?
あ！着いた！
Ah! It reached!
「トン」って感じした！
I felt a thud!
あとはズルズルと引きずる
Now we slowly drag it along.
するとシロギスというのが釣れる
Oh, so apparently you can catch Japanese whiting here.
本当かなぁ？
Is that true?
なんか突かれてる感覚あるよ！
I feel something nibbling!
本当？
Really?
なんかツンツンされてる
It's poking at it.
餌だけ食われてねぇかな？
Is it just stealing the bait?
どうなんだろうね？
I wonder.
シロギスって頭いいのかな？
Are Japanese whiting smart?
食い逃げされてたらどうしよう
What if they eat it and run off?
でもちっちゃいから脳みそちっちゃいんじゃないの？
But they're small, so wouldn't their brains be tiny?
ミオしゃ刺すね～！
Mio-sha, that's harsh!
うん
Yeah.
ちなみにアジ釣りに行った時はさ
By the way, when I went horse mackerel fishing...
うん
Yeah?
波と同化しろ
They told me to "Become one with the waves."
海と一体化したら釣れた！
And when I became one with the ocean, I caught one!
じゃあ今日も波と一体化しなよ！早く！
Then become one with the waves today too! Hurry!
分かってるよそんなの！
I know that already!
ミオヒット！？
Ah, I might have got one!
来たか？
Did you get a bite?
マジで来てる！
Wait, really? You got a bite!
引いてるよ！
Isn't it biting? It's pulling!
来てないわ～
Nope, nothing...
来てなかった…
There was nothing...
スバルも一回確認してみよ！
Let me check Subaru's line too!
なんか海藻ついて…
There's some seaweed on it...
え、嘘！？
Wait, no way!
釣れた！！
I caught one!!
釣れてるよ！
It's caught!
ミオちゃん釣れるぞここ！
Mio-chan, they bite here!
本当に？
Really?
やっぱり海と一体化する事なんや！
It really is about becoming one with the ocean!
今一体化してた…？
Were you becoming one just now...?
してたしてた！
Yes, I was!
ホロライブ釣り部
I love fishing. Maybe I should form the "Hololive Fishing Club."
釣り部
Fishing Club.
これ砂の感じがクンクン来てるのか…
Is this the feeling of the sandy bottom dragging...?
私も「これ砂かな～」と思って分かんねぇなと思ってた
I was also thinking, "Is this sand?" and couldn't tell.
今度こそ…！？
Oh, I might have got one!
来てんじゃない？
Isn't it a bite?
なんかグイってなった気がする
I feel like there was a tug.
来てるって！ミオちゃん頑張れ！
It's on! Hang in there, Mio-chan!
マジで！？
Really!?
本当に？でもなんか軽くなったかも…
Really? But it might have gotten lighter...
ミオ１匹目
It's on! It's on, it's on!
やったー！
Yay!
海と一体化するのが大事！
Becoming one with the ocean is important!
取れたー！
I caught it!
もう一匹釣ろうぜ！
Let's catch another one!
頑張りたいね！
I want to try my best!
どうしよう 釣りの案件来たら
What if we get a fishing sponsorship deal?
釣りの案件！
A fishing deal!
やべぇ 来てるかも！
Oh crap, I think I have one!
来てる？
You do?
逃げられちゃったかな…？
Did it get away...?
でもなんか引いてる…？
But is it pulling...?
上げてみないと意外と分かんなくな…
You won't know until you pull it up...
でしょ？私も途中まで…
Right? Me too, until halfway through...
まさかの２匹！！
Unbelievable, two fish!!
上げて上げて上げて！
Pull it up, pull it up!
釣れてるような釣れてないようなとか言ってたら２匹釣れてる！
While saying if it was caught or not, there were two!
美味そう！
Looks delicious!
え、やべぇ釣れてるかも！
Oh, I think I got one too!
スバル入れ食い状態！
Subaru is on a spree!
ほら、釣れてる！
Look, it's caught!
来てる気はする…！
I feel like it's biting...!
来てない…
Nothing...
魚って意外に殺意感じ取るらしい
Apparently fish can sense bloodlust surprisingly well.
じゃあウチは殺意が強い…？
So I have strong bloodlust...?
絶対に釣ってやる…！！
"I'll definitely catch you...!!"
なるほどね
I see.
ミオちゃん今何考えてるの？
Mio-chan, what are you thinking right now?
釣りって…
Fishing is...
無だなあって。
...so empty.
これ無になりにみんな来てんだもん！
Everyone comes here to clear their minds!
そうなの！？
Really!?
海見てボーッとするついでに魚釣ってんだよ
They catch fish while staring blankly at the sea.
そうなんだ
I see.
デジタルデトックス
Perfect for a digital detox.
でしょ？
Right?
波のリズムに身を任せる
Surrendering to the rhythm of the waves.
そうだ、波のリズムに身を任せ…
That's it, surrender to the waves...
ミオヒット！？
A bite!
来てる来てる！絶対来てると思う！
It's on! I'm sure it's on!
ミオ２匹目
Mio's 2nd catch
ミオちゃん２匹目！
Mio-chan's second fish!
今の気持ちをどうぞ！
How do you feel right now?
嬉しいです！
I'm so happy!
ピチピチです！
It's super fresh!
帰るか
Should we head back after one more try?
早い！
So fast!
どう？ミオちゃん体力的に
How are you feeling stamina-wise, Mio-chan?
全然大丈夫だけど！
I'm totally fine!
走ってる時よりラク
Easier than when running.
ふざけんじゃねぇよ！
Don't give me that!
良くないみたい！！
Sounds like my Ozora Cruise isn't any good!!
今日は釣った魚食べられるから！
Today we get to eat the fish we catch!
キスってさ どういう種類の食べ方思い浮かぶ？
What kind of dishes come to mind for whiting?
天ぷらじゃない？
Isn't it tempura?
やっぱ天ぷらかな？
I guess tempura, right?
お刺身もいけるんだって！
You can also have it as sashimi!
大空クルーズの生贄
Sacrifices for Ozora Cruise
船酔いしなさそうで 楽しんでくれそうな人がいい？
Someone who won't get seasick and would enjoy it?
うん
Yeah.
千速とかは？
How about Chihaya?
千速いいじゃん！
Chihaya would be great!
ちは絶対楽しんでくれるでしょ！
Chi will definitely enjoy it!
絶対楽しんでくれそうなタイプ
She's definitely the type to enjoy it.
じゃあちはに一言！
Give Chi a message then!
意外と酔うから 絶対に酔い止めは飲んできた方がいいよ
You'll get surprisingly seasick, so take motion sickness medicine!
千速バイク乗ってる…
Chihaya rides a motorcycle...
車！
A car!
酔わないんじゃないの？
Won't she be fine then?
どうかな～？
I wonder.
ちは！来年乗ってくれよな！
Chi! Ride with us next year!
でもノリノリで来てくれそう！
But she'll probably come super hyped!
鬼ノリいいからな！
She's got great energy!
莉々華とかも良さそう！
Ririka seems like a good choice too!
何か起きるか分かんない
You never know what's gonna happen!
スゲエの釣りに行きたい
I want to go fishing for something awesome!
なるほどね
Makes sense.
フブキもめっちゃ釣り好きだからさ
Fubuki loves fishing too, you know!
そうなの！？
She does!?
だって事あるごとにゲーム内で 釣りばっかしてるじゃん
Yeah, she fishes in games whenever she can!
あれゲームだからとかじゃなくて？
Isn't that just because it's in a game?
違うよ～！
No way~!
釣りガチャ要素強いしな！
Fishing does have a strong gacha element!
晴れ
Sunny weather
こんなにバチバチに晴れて
The weather turned out so insanely sunny!
釣れてんじゃない？
Isn't there something on your line?
どうだ？ どうだ？
How is it? How is it?
どうだ？ 重い気がする！
How is it? It feels heavy!
ミオちゃんデカいのきてんじゃないの？
Mio-chan, didn't you hook a big one?
釣れたか？
Did I catch it?
釣れたー！
I caught one!
やったー！
Yay!
ミオちゃん、シロギス！
Mio-chan, it's a Japanese whiting!
元気いっぱいだ！
It's so full of energy!
うわ、クラゲだ！
Whoa, a jellyfish!
すごい、浮いてる！
Wow, it's floating!
本当だ！
It really is!
最近スバル、クラゲ食うのにハマってるから
I've been really into eating jellyfish lately!
そうなの？ 持って帰る？
Really? Do you want to take it home?
いや要らない… 怖いやん！
No, I don't... It's scary!
刺されると痛てぇ
It hurts if you get stung!
やべぇ、これ釣れてる、多分
Oh, man, I think I've caught something.
来てるか？
Is it biting?
引いてる、引いてる！
It's pulling, it's pulling!
これは絶対釣れてる！
I definitely got one!
ほらー！ キター！
Look! Here it comes!
釣れてるー！ やったー！
I caught it! Yay!
ミオちゃん、俺がエントリーしたい！
Mio-chan, I want to count us down!
いいよ
Sure.
行くよ
Here I go.
いち！
One!
にの！
Two!
さん！
Three!
おせぇ…
So slow...
言うの忘れてたなって、今！
I realized just now I forgot to say "three"!
果たして釣れるのか？
Will we actually catch anything?
「ちょん」としました！
It gave a little "tug"!
あとはミオちゃん頑張って
Now, do your best, Mio-chan!
「ちょん」ってするの分かったんだ！
Oh, you could tell it gave a tug!
うん
Yeah.
あ、引いてる…？ え、嘘？
Ah, is it pulling...? Wait, really?
あ、本当だ！ 引いてる、引いてる！
Oh, it really is! It's pulling!
引いてる！ なんか引いてるかも！
It's pulling! I think something's pulling!
ゆっくり、ゆっくり… なんか引いてるかも！
Slowly, slowly... Something is definitely pulling!
頑張れ！
You can do it!
よいしょ！ 釣れたー！
Here we go! We caught it!
ラストフィッシング！
Last fishing!
ラストフィッシングや！ やったー！
It's the last fishing! Yay!
という事で！
And so!
本日の釣果がこちら！
Here is today's total catch!
ねぇすごいよミオちゃん、マジ！
Woah, Mio-chan, this is seriously amazing!
14匹釣れてんだよ！
We caught 14 of them!
という事でミオちゃん！ 釣ったやつ！
So, Mio-chan! Don't you want to eat...
すぐ食べたいと思わないか？
...what we just caught right away?
た、食べられるんですか？ 生は無理だよ！
C-Can we eat them? I can't eat raw fish!
「生でいけ」とは言ってない！
I didn't say to eat it raw!
このままちょっと踊り食いはね… 狼と言えど！
Eating them alive like this is a bit much... even for a wolf!
これからこれを料理して！ 食べたいと思います！
We're going to cook these up and eat them!
という事で！ さっき釣った魚がこちらです！
And so, here are the fish we just caught!
えー！ すごーい！ もう面影ない！
Eh! Amazing! They don't look like fish anymore!
そうだよ！ 完全にな！
That's right! Completely transformed!
釣った後はやっぱ！ 釣りたての魚を食べるのが醍醐味！
The best part of fishing is eating fresh fish right after!
贅沢！
Such a luxury!
食べようぜ〜！
Let's eat!
いただきます！
Bon appétit!
何から食べる？
What should we eat first?
お刺身でしょ！
Sashimi, obviously!
お刺身にできるぐらいの デカい奴って珍しいらしいよ！
Big ones that can be made into sashimi are pretty rare!
そうなの？
Really?
いただきまーす！ わー、すごい！
Bon appétit! Wow, amazing!
ミオちゃんが釣ったやつだよ！
That's the one you caught, Mio-chan!
本当…？
Really...?
適当パチこいてんだろ！
You're just making that up!
なんでそんな事言うの！
Why would you say that?!
ミオちゃんが釣ったやつかもしれない！
It really could be the one you caught!
分かんないだろ！ いただきまーす！
You wouldn't know! Bon appétit!
美味しい！
Delicious!
歯応えがある！
It's so nice and chewy!
甘い！
It's sweet!
結構噛み応えがしっかりしてて 甘いね！
It has a nice firm bite to it, and it's sweet!
見て！ プリプリ！ 凄い！ 肉厚だ！
Look! So plump! Wow, it's really thick!
普通のお刺身ではない
It's not like regular sashimi!
釣りたてのお刺身美味いんだよ！
Freshly caught sashimi is so good!
釣りたてってやっぱり違うよね
Freshly caught really makes a difference!
天ぷらも食べよう！
Let's try the tempura too!
いただきまーす！
Bon appétit!
うまー！ 美味い！
So good! Delicious!
これは美味い！
This is amazing!
でしょ！ スバルが作ったわけじゃない
Right?! Though Subaru didn't make it...
作っていただいたんですけど 最高です！
It was prepared for us, but it's the best!
ミオちゃんどうだった？
How was it, Mio-chan?
大空クルーズ★3
You rated Oozora Cruise 3 stars before, right?
なんと今ならこの！ プロの人が作ったご飯付き！
But now, it includes meals cooked by professionals!
★5になるに決まってる！
It's guaranteed to be 5 stars!
イエーイ！
Yay!
それではこのご飯を食べながら 最後は「さよなら」したいと思う
Now then, while enjoying this food, let's wrap up and say goodbye!
もう「さよなら」のお時間なんですか？
Is it already time to say goodbye?
そうだよ！
Yes, it is!
そうだよ、朝から！
That's right, since early morning!
超早朝からさ、行ってさ、ルール教えてもらってさ！
We went out super early, learned the rules, and everything!
大空クルーズが出港してさ、釣りしてさ、これ作ってもらってさ！
Oozora Cruise set sail, we fished, and had this cooked for us!
聞いてる？
Are you listening to me?
それじゃあ！ 大空クルーズ！ これにて！
Well then! Oozora Cruise, with this...
第一部 終
...Part 1 comes to an end!
じゃあみんな！ またね〜！
See you all later!
ばいば〜い！
Bye-bye!
ご来場…？
Thank you for coming...?
ご… ご…
Th... Th...
船に乗れー！
Get on the boat! Bye-bye!
次はお前だ！！
You're next!!